<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The rational pilgrim on The Rational Pilgrim</title><link>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/</link><description>Recent content in The rational pilgrim on The Rational Pilgrim</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>1. Introduction</title><link>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/intro/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/intro/</guid><description>&lt;h1 class="custom-title"> 1. Introduction&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>For thousands of years, humanity has witnessed phenomena it could not explain and often saw them as signs or actions of the divine. Over time, however, science has advanced, shedding light where once there were only mysteries and beliefs.&lt;br>
In the Middle Ages, for example, the Black Death was interpreted as divine punishment. Illnesses were seen as consequences of sin or as tests of faith. Today, we know that microbes, viruses, and parasites cause many of these diseases, while others are linked to genetics. Medicine has made great strides in uncovering their origins and developing treatments.&lt;br>
Likewise, an eclipse was once feared as an omen from the gods. Now astronomy can predict exactly when and where it will occur, thanks to our understanding of orbits and planetary alignments.&lt;br>
Isn’t it worth asking, then, what still belongs to the realm of the divine?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>2. Approaching the Spiritual Quest Scientifically?</title><link>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/method/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2025 23:49:30 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/method/</guid><description>&lt;h1 class="custom-title"> 2. Approaching the Spiritual Quest Scientifically?&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Even what seems most concrete, rational, and undeniable — like mathematics — ultimately rests on assumptions. Any proven statement takes the form: &lt;em>if we assume XX, then we can prove YY through reasoning&lt;/em> (even if the assumptions are not always stated explicitly). These basic assumptions are called axioms.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to the Larousse dictionary, an &lt;strong>axiom&lt;/strong> is:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>In Aristotelian logic, the starting point of reasoning, considered self-evident and not demonstrable.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The initial statement of an axiomatized theory, serving as the foundation for further demonstrations.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>An unquestioned proposition, accepted as the basis of an intellectual, social, or moral framework — a truth admitted by all without discussion.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>For example, Euclidean plane geometry (geometry on a flat surface, like a sheet of paper) is built on five axioms, known as &lt;em>Euclid’s postulates&lt;/em> (
 &lt;a href="http://www.bibmath.net">bibmath.net&lt;/a>):&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>4. Toward the Existence of the God of Philosophers</title><link>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/aff2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/aff2/</guid><description>&lt;h2 class="custom-title"> 4. Toward the Existence of the God of Philosophers&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In the previous chapter, we started from the following axioms (see Chapter 2 for a definition of axioms):&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote style="border-left: 4px solid #007acc; background-color: #f0f8ff; padding: 1em; border-radius: 6px; margin: 1.5em 0;"> 
&lt;strong>Axiom 1:&lt;/strong> Everything that begins to exist has a cause.&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Axiom 2:&lt;/strong> The universe began to exist.&lt;br> 
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>From these, we derived the following statement:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote style="border-left: 4px solid #007acc; background-color: #f0f8ff; padding: 1em; border-radius: 6px; margin: 1.5em 0;"> 
&lt;strong>Statement 1:&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Since the universe had a beginning, it must depend on a cause outside itself — an uncreated, immaterial, timeless, supremely powerful, and intentional or personal reality. 
This reality constitutes the &lt;strong>First Cause&lt;/strong> of all that exists.
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>But can we go further? Can we show that this First Cause is not a mere impersonal force, but a being endowed with intelligence and will — what philosophers have long called &lt;em>God&lt;/em>, not in the religious sense, but in the &lt;strong>philosophical&lt;/strong> one?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>5. Which Divine Revelation to Follow?</title><link>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/pluralite/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/pluralite/</guid><description>&lt;h1 class="custom-title"> 5. Which Divine Revelation to Follow?&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>In the previous chapters, we presented several considerations that make the following two premises (or axioms) reasonable: everything that begins to exist has a cause (&lt;strong>Axiom 1&lt;/strong>), and the universe began to exist (&lt;strong>Axiom 2&lt;/strong>). From these foundations, we concluded that the universe depends on a reality without beginning, unmoving, uncreated, necessary, and outside time — the first cause of all that exists (&lt;strong>Statement 1&lt;/strong>). This first cause appears as an immaterial, eternal, necessary, intelligent, free, and unique being, which philosophical reasoning allows us to identify as the God of philosophers (&lt;strong>Statement 2&lt;/strong>). From this analysis follow three consequences: God is omniscient, omnipresent, and omnipotent; He is perfect — fully complete in Himself; and He is just, acting according to truth and goodness.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>3.1 The Big Bang Theory and Alternative Models</title><link>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/aff1/section1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/aff1/section1/</guid><description>&lt;h2 class="custom-title"> 3.1 The Big Bang Theory and Alternative Models&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Since the early 20th century, a series of major scientific discoveries has profoundly reshaped our understanding of the universe. Far from the idea of a static, eternal cosmos, astronomical observations — notably Edwin Hubble’s measurements of galactic redshifts — revealed an expanding universe. This cosmic dynamic led to the development of the Big Bang theory, according to which the universe emerged from an extremely hot, dense state about 13.7 billion years ago &lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. Today the theory is strongly supported by observations such as the cosmic microwave background and the primordial abundance of light elements. It was not always universally accepted, however. Other models — like the steady-state universe or cyclic scenarios — have attempted to address the same data while avoiding the notion of an absolute beginning. Yet these alternatives face theoretical and empirical limits that make them less convincing than the elegance and robustness of the standard cosmological model.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>3.2 Is It Possible to Cross an Infinite Past?</title><link>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/aff1/section2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/aff1/section2/</guid><description>&lt;h2 class="custom-title"> 3.2 Is It Possible to Cross an Infinite Past?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Another argument for a beginning of time and the universe rests on a mathematical intuition: the past cannot be infinite, because it would be impossible to &lt;em>cross&lt;/em> such an infinity and arrive at the present moment.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="potential-infinity-vs-actual-infinity">
 Potential Infinity vs. Actual Infinity
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#potential-infinity-vs-actual-infinity">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>It is important to distinguish two fundamental notions of infinity:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Potential infinity&lt;/strong>: a quantity that can increase without bound but is always finite at each stage. For example, counting 1, 2, 3… without ever reaching an “infinite number.” In mathematics this corresponds to the concept of a limit, where a value tends toward infinity without ever attaining it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>3.3 Why Is There Something Rather Than Nothing?</title><link>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/aff1/section3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/aff1/section3/</guid><description>&lt;h2 class="custom-title"> 3.3 Why Is There Something Rather Than Nothing?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In the previous sections, we saw that &lt;strong>the universe very likely had a beginning&lt;/strong>. Whether through the Big Bang theory or the impossibility of crossing an infinite regress of past events, all evidence suggests that the cosmos is not eternal in the past.&lt;br>
We are therefore faced with a profound and dizzying question:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Why is there something rather than nothing?&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>If the universe began to exist, then &lt;strong>something outside the universe must have caused that beginning&lt;/strong>. This brings us to the &lt;strong>Kalām Cosmological Argument&lt;/strong>, revitalized in modern philosophy by William Lane Craig.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>3.4 A Philosophical Portrait of the First Cause</title><link>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/aff1/section4/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/aff1/section4/</guid><description>&lt;h2 class="custom-title"> 3.4 A Philosophical Portrait of the First Cause &lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We have seen that if the universe began to exist, and if everything that begins to exist has a cause, it logically follows that &lt;strong>the universe has a cause&lt;/strong>.&lt;br>
But what kind of cause could account for the very existence of everything that exists?
A philosophical analysis of the necessary conditions for such a cause reveals several essential properties:&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="1-a-non-physical-cause">
 1. A &lt;strong>Non-Physical Cause&lt;/strong>
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#1-a-non-physical-cause">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>The cause of the universe cannot be physical or material, for the simple reason that matter itself began to exist with the universe.&lt;br>
If matter has a beginning, its cause cannot be composed of what it brings into being. The cause must therefore be &lt;strong>immaterial&lt;/strong>, independent of particles, fields, or physical laws.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>3.5 Conclusions</title><link>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/aff1/section5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://therationalpilgrim.github.io/web/aff1/section5/</guid><description>&lt;h2 class="custom-title"> 3.5 Conclusions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Today, the Big Bang model remains the most successful scientific explanation of the origin and evolution of the universe.&lt;br>
It aligns with the major observations — from the cosmic microwave background to the abundance of light elements and the formation of large-scale structures.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It is therefore neither irrational nor scientifically unfounded to think that the universe had a beginning — an origin point about 13.8 billion years ago, characterized by an extremely hot and dense state.&lt;br>
From both philosophical and mathematical perspectives, the idea of an &lt;em>actually infinite&lt;/em> past presents serious difficulties: a truly infinite sequence of successive events could never be &lt;strong>crossed&lt;/strong> step by step — yet we have clearly reached the present.&lt;br>
This suggests that time had a beginning and that the series of past events is not infinite. On this basis, we can state as &lt;strong>Axiom 2&lt;/strong> that the universe began to exist.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>